Deutsches Primatenzentrum GmbH, Kellnerweg 4, 37077, Göttingen, Germany

■ NSirmpilatze@dpz.eu | 🐐 www.nsirmpilatze.com/ | 🖸 niksirbi | 🔰 @niksirbi | 🎓 Nikoloz Sirmpilatze

### Research Interest

My research focuses on the effects of anesthesia on brain function - a topic that I explore with functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI). I collect and analyze neuroimaging data from multiple mammalian species, including humans, non-human primates and rodents. I am particularly interested in what sorts of activities arise in the brain across various depths of anesthesia, either spontaneously or as a reaction to sensory stimuli.

### **Education**

### **German Primate Center - Functional Imaging Lab**

Göttingen, Germany

PHD IN NEUROIMAGING

2017 - present

- · Working thesis title: fMRI mapping of anesthesia-induced burst suppression across multiple species
- · Advisor: Prof. Dr. Susann Boretius

### **Georg-August University of Göttingen - IMPRS for Neurosciences**

Göttingen, Germany

MSc in Neuroscience

2015 - 2017

- · Thesis title: The temporal stability of BOLD fMRI measurements in medetomidine-anesthetized rats
- Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Susann Boretius
- Final grade: excellent 1.1 (1.0 down to 5.0)

# Aristotle University of Thessaloniki Thessaloniki, Greece

DOCTOR OF MEDICINE (MD)

Oct. 2009 - Jul. 2015

• Final grade: excellent 9.43/10 (valedictorian)

## **Teaching Experience**

#### Teaching Assistant for Introduction to MRI/fMRI

Göttingen, Germany

IMPRS FOR NEUROSCIENCES MSc PROGRAM

2017 - 2019

- Gave tutorials and hands-on method courses of fMRI acquisition and analysis
- Workload: approx. 1 week per year for 3 years

### **Supervisor for Master Student**

Göttingen, Germany

IMPRS FOR NEUROSCIENCES MSc PROGRAM

Oct. 2018 - Mar. 2019

• Dmytro Nesterenko: Resting state connectivity and negative BOLD responses

### Supervisor for Lab Rotations

Göttingen, Germany

IMPRS FOR NEUROSCIENCES MSc PROGRAM

2019 - 2020

- Hanna Dubrovska: Ipsilateral negative BOLD response during the motor task in the HCP dataset
- · Anna Liashenko: Changes in resting state functional connectivity after the neurofeedback training of anterior midcingulate cortex (aMCC)
- Duration of each rotation: 8 weeks

#### **Community Teaching Assistant for Medical Neuroscience**

Online

MOOC OFFERED BY DUKE UNIVERSITY THROUGH WWW.COURSERA.ORG

Jan. - Mar. 2013

· Monitored student forums and answered questions

## Teaching Assistant for Neuroanatomy

Thessaloniki, Greece

LABORATORY OF DESCRIPTIVE ANATOMY, ARISTOTLE UNIVERSITY MEDICAL SCHOOL

Feb. - May 2011

Assisted during practical course on brain dissection

### **Extracurricular Activities**

**Brainhack Comparative MRI** 

London, UK Sep. 2019

Gained experience with collaborative coding projects

Neurizons Conference Göttingen, Germany

ORGANIZER

PARTICIPANT

2017 - 2020

- Neurizons is a biennial neuroscience conference organized by students
- Was part of the organizing committee from 2017 to 2020
- · Was responsible for graphic design in 2018 and oversaw the migration to a virtual format in 2020

### **Introduction to Data Science**

Göttingen, Germany

PARTICIPANT

Feb. 2018

- 1-week course organized by the GGNB Graduate School
- · Gained experience with the scientific python ecosystem (numpy, scipy, pandas, matplotlib, scikit-learn)

#### **Regression Modelling**

Göttingen, Germany

PARTICIPANT

PARTICIPANT

May 2017

- 1-week course organized by the Leibniz Science Campus Primate Cognition
- · Learned about building regression models with R

#### **Laboratory Animal Science Course on Primates**

Göttingen, Germany

Nov. 2016

- E-learning module followed by 1-week on-site course
- Organized by the European Primate Network (EUPRIM-Net)

#### **Laboratory Animal Science**

Göttingen, Germany

Mar. - Oct. 2016

PARTICIPANT

- 20-hours theoretical module followed by 1-week practical course
- Organized by the Central Animal Facility, University Medical Center Göttingen
- · According to the recommendations of FELASA (Category B)

## Stipends & Awards \_\_\_\_\_

2019	Magna cum Laude Merit Award & Educational Stipend, 27 <sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting of the ISMRM	Montreal, Canada
2017	<b>Student Support Program</b> , 34 <sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting of the ESMRMB	Barcelona, Spain
2015	Full MSc Student Scholarship, German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD)	Germany
2010	Undergraduate distinction, Yearly Stipend from the State Scholarships Foundation of Greece (IKY)	Greece

### **Skills**

MRI acquisition Familiar with Bruker (Paravision) and Siemens Prisma platformsMRI analysis FSL, ANTS, nipype, Freesurfer, AFNI, BrainVoyager, nilearn

**Programming** Python, R, Bash, git, MEX

**Animals** Rodent handling, anesthesia, surgery, stereotaxic injections

**Languages** Greek, Georgian, English, German, Russian

## **Research Output**

#### PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J. & Boretius, S. Temporal stability of fMRI in medetomidine-anesthetized rats. *Scientific Reports* **9**, 16673. ISSN: 2045-2322 (Nov. 2019).
- 2. Hafner, G., Guy, J., Witte, M., Truschow, P., Rüppel, A., **Sirmpilatze**, N., Dadarwal, R., Boretius, S. & Staiger, J. F. Increased Callosal Connectivity in Reeler Mice Revealed by Brain-Wide Input Mapping of VIP Neurons in Barrel Cortex. *Cerebral Cortex*. bhaa280. ISSN: 1047-3211 (Nov. 2020).
- 3. Milham, M. *et al.* Accelerating the Evolution of Nonhuman Primate Neuroimaging. *Neuron* **105,** 600–603. ISSN: 0896-6273 (Feb. 2020).

### **PREPRINTS**

1. Messinger, A., **Sirmpilatze**, N., Heuer, K., Loh, K. K., Mars, R. B., Sein, J., Xu, T., Glen, D., Jung, B., Seidlitz, J., Taylor, P., Toro, R., Garza-Villarreal, E. A., Sponheim, C., Wang, X., Benn, R. A., Cagna, B., Dadarwal, R., Evrard, H. C., Garcia-Saldivar, P., Giavasis, S., Hartig, R., Lepage, C., Liu, C., Majka, P., Merchant, H., Milham, M. P., Rosa, M. G., Tasserie, J., Uhrig, L., Margulies, D. S. & Klink, P. C. A collaborative resource platform for non-human primate neuroimaging. *bioRxiv* (2020).

### **CONFERENCE CONTRIBUTIONS**

- Sirmpilatze, N., Baudewig, J., Mylius, J., Golkowski, D., Ranft, A., Ilg, R., Paasonen, J., Gröhn, O. & Boretius, S. fMRI mapping of anesthesia-induced burst suppression across multiple mammalian species in 15<sup>th</sup> European Molecular Imaging Meeting (virtual) Online Talk (2020).
- 2. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J., Mylius, J., Golkowski, D., Ranft, A., Ilg, R. & Boretius, S. *Using BOLD fMRI to map anesthesia-induced burst suppression in humans and non-human primates* in 27<sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting of the International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine Talk (2019).
- 3. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J. & Boretius, S. *Are fMRI measurements in medetomidine-anesthetized rats tempo-rally stable?* in 27<sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting of the International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine Digital Poster (2019).
- 4. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J., Kötz, K. & Boretius, S. *Optimizing medetomidine anesthesia for fMRI in rats* in 11<sup>th</sup> *Forum of Neuroscience, Federation of European Neuroscience Societies* Poster (2018).
- 5. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J., Kötz, K. & Boretius, S. *The temporal stability of BOLD fMRI measurements in medeto-midine anesthetized rats* in 34<sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting of the European Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine and Biology Poster (2017).

### **OPEN DATASETS**

- 1. **Sirmpilatze**, N. & Klink, P. C. *RheMAP: Non-linear warps between common rhesus macaque brain templates* (Zenodo, May 2020).
- 2. **Sirmpilatze**, N., Baudewig, J. & Boretius, S. *Temporal stability of fMRI in medetomidine-anesthetized rats* (Open-Neuro, Nov. 2019).